<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The marriners card and compass. Or The best way to attain heaven amidst a sinfull and crooked generation. By William Harvey, minister of the Word</title>
            <author>Harvey, William, fl. 1657-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218426</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830025</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830025</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43039)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2031:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The marriners card and compass. Or The best way to attain heaven amidst a sinfull and crooked generation. By William Harvey, minister of the Word</title>
                  <author>Harvey, William, fl. 1657-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Heading on p. 1 reads: John. 14. 6. I am the way, the truth, and the life.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Wing reel guide incorrectly lists item as located at 2030:18.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34472:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Marriners Card and Compaſs.</hi> OR THE BEST WAY TO ATTAIN HEAVEN Amidſt a Sinfull and Crooked <hi>GENERATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM HARVEY,</hi> Miniſter of the Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>AUGUST.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Vae etiam laudabili vita hominum, ſi remotâ miſericordiâ diſcutias eam.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>—Haec via ducit in urbem.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34472:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34472:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable <hi>ANN</hi> Counteſs Dowager of SCARSDEL, And To the reſt of that Noble Family, Grace, Mercy, and Peace, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He world (for the moſt part) is like the <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs-Tree,</hi> long and fruitleſs; and like <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> ſtrange Soyl, for all the ſweet ſhowres that fall upon, it it's ſtill
<pb facs="tcp:34472:3"/>dry as duſt. The cauſe of it is either ignorance or negligence, want of <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the will of God, or <hi>Non-Improvement.</hi> I have endeavoured to remove theſe Obſtructions, and to take the rubs out of the way. There are but two extreams, Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Deſperation, which like <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of all the veſſeds they met with. Where theſe waters break out, they beat down all before them. They are alike dangerous (faith <hi>Chryſost.</hi>) For Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption falls him that ſtandeth, and Deſperation after a fall admits no riſing. This ſmall Tract (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam)
<pb facs="tcp:34472:3"/>by Gods aſſiſtance will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the one, and reform the other. It will be an eye to the ignorant, and a ſpur to the negligent; for it treats only of Chriſt, and as the Star the Wiſe men, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct them to him. But I am loth to take too large a ſurvey in ſo ſmall a piece of ground. They that write muſt not forget that Rule of the Orator, <hi>ut titulum legant,</hi> to read the Title of their Books, leaſt like the gates of <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> it proves bigger then the City it ſelf. I was ambitions to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to your Honour, that it might kiſs your hand, which hath been ſo often open to men of my
<pb facs="tcp:34472:4"/>calling and condition, and in particular to my ſelf, the meaneſt of them who ſerve at the Altar. Now the God of Heaven be your continual guard and guide; his Bleſſings in a plurality light upon your Honour, and your whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, as the dew on <hi>Gideons</hi> Fleece. This ſhall alwayes be the unfeigned Prayers of.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble, and grateful Servant,</hi> William Harvey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34472:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 14. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are an anſwer to the precedent verſe, and they are Allegoricall, rate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adorn'd, partly metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically, and partly Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymically, and they are brought in, to inform <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the reſt of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples more fully in the way of Salvation. We know not (ſaith <hi>Thomas)</hi> whither thou goeſt, and how can we know the way? Our Saviour preſently reſolv's him in the words of my Text. <hi>I am the way, the truth and the Life. Aurea Sententia,</hi> A golden Sentence. The wife men of the Eaſt opened their treaſures, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto him guifts, even Gold, Frankincence, and Myrrh; but he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34472:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>unto us guifts more precious, in that they fit the Soul in her divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs to Heaven, and as the Angels, <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> carry it into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome.) But I will come to the ſeverall branches of the Text. And they are three, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ia, veritis, &amp; vita.</hi> The way the truth, and the Life.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt is the <hi>way docendo,</hi> by way of teaching, becauſe he alone inſtructs in the way to happineſs. The Law is our Schoolmaſter to bring us to Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24. and Chriſt is our Schoolmaſter who brings us to Heaven. he is that <hi>pillar</hi> of a cloud and fire leading us the way to the Heavenly <hi>Canaan, Exod.</hi> 13.21. St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>No man hath ſeen God at any time, the only begotten Son which is in the boſome of the Father he hath declared him. John.</hi> 1.18. He is the true <hi>Mercuries</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that directs the poor wandring tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller the right way to his heavenly Manſion. None but he can fit us for that bleſſed Academy above, were we ſhall all) be Fellow-Communers with the Saints and bleſſed Angels.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is the way <hi>promerendo,</hi> by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34472:5"/>way of Meriting. Conerning this nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is that of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 5.16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>For if by one mans offence, death reigned, by one much more they which receive abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of grace, and the guift of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall reign in Life by one Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. read the Text. He alone is that <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who hath broken the Cords of our <hi>Sins</hi> from us, by which we were ſo faſt bound, and with that woman in the Goſpell, even bowed together. That ſtrong man Satan, <hi>by him</hi> is overcome, and his armour wherein he truſted, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him, and his ſpoiles divided. <hi>Luke.</hi> 11.22. The Apoſtle to the <hi>Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſaith, <hi>In whom we have redemption through his blood, even the forgiveneſs of our Sins, Col.</hi> 1.14. and v. 20. (Having made peace through the blood of his Croſs) by him to reconcile all things to himſelf. To omit a cloud of witneſſes; St. <hi>Peter</hi> poſitively thus, <hi>Neither is their Salvation in any other; for there is none other name under Heaven given among men whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> Acts. 4.12. And thus he is the way <hi>promerendo,</hi> by way of merit.</p>
            <p>Thirdly He is the way <hi>applicando,</hi> by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34472:6"/>way of application; And that in Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſpects. <hi>Firſt</hi> by his word; ſo the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of Life.</hi> Pſ. 16.11. And in another Pſalme <hi>I will inſtruct thee, and teach thee in the way which you ſhalt go. I will guide thee with mine eye.</hi> Pſ. 32 8. <hi>Secondly</hi> by his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which God hath not only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us according to his mercy, by the waſhing of regeneration, and renewing of the holy Ghoſt, which he ſhed on us abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly through Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour, that being juſtified by his grace, we ſhould be made heirs according to the hope of eternall Life. Titus 3.5, 6, 7. But alſo he doth Confirm unto us as by undoubted Seals and aſſurances, the way of Salvation, righteouſneſs, and eternall Life. So the Apoſtle ſpeaking of <hi>Abraham. And he recieved the ſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gne of Circumciſion, a Seal of the righteouſneſs of faith, which he had being yet uncircumciſed; that he might be the Father of all them that believe though they be not circumciſed, that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs might be imputed to them alſo. Ro.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Thirdly</hi> By holy and fervent prayers, According to that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> Eph. 2.18.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34472:6"/>
               <hi>For through him we both have an acceſs by one Spirit unto the Father, &amp;c.</hi> chap. 3.12. <hi>In whom we have boldneſs and acceſs with confidence by the faith of him.</hi> And to the Romans he ſaith, <hi>For ye have nor received the Spirit of Bondage again to fear: but ye have received the Spirit of ad<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ption, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we cry Abba Father.</hi> Rom. 8.15. To this purpoſe we are commanded in our <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> to ſupplicate Almighty God in that ſweet Epithete and name of Father. <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="*" place="margin">ut vere creda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus eum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum verum parrem, noſque ejus veros fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os eſſe: ut eo confidentius plena fiducia adcum acceda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, eumque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voeemus; quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus liberos certa fiducia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid aparenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis potere Luth, in Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Catechet.</note> that (as <hi>Mart. Luther</hi> expounds it) We might believe him to be our true Father, and we his very Sons, and that we ſhould come unto him more confidently, in a full aſſurance, and might call upon him, even as we ſee Children with Confidence beg any thing of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. For which cauſe he is ſaid to be our advocate, 1. <hi>Ep. John</hi> 2.1. <hi>And if any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34472:7"/>Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous, &amp;c.</hi> And by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> our Mediator, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 25. <hi>For there is one God and one Mediatour between God and men, the man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, <hi>per exemplum,</hi> by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in ſhewing us the way how to live in mutual love and amity one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For this we have a fair copy to write by, John 13.15. <hi>For I have given you an example, that ye ſhould do as I have done to you,</hi> and what is that, even a low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention, a rare bird on the earth <hi>nigro ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millima Cigno,</hi> like unto a black Swan; hear it, <hi>If I then your Lord and Maſter have waſhed your feet,</hi> what ſaid I, waſhed your feet? O rare humility! <hi>ye alſo ought</hi> (and all the reaſon in the world) <hi>to waſh one anothers feet.</hi> v. 14. Secondly, In ſhewing us how we ſhould undergoe and ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and perſecutions in this life. Herein likewiſe he hath beaten our way before us. 1. Pet. 2.21. <hi>For even hereunto were ye called; becauſe Christ alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi> And now I come to application.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt be the only way to happineſs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34472:7"/>as is clear by the premiſes; then by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, all who affect and follow any other way beſide, without, and againſt Chriſt cannot be ſaved. Let the Turke dream of an <hi>Elizium</hi> and fancy what car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pleaſures he pleaſe in another world; he will find one day he <hi>built</hi> but Caſtles in the Air, and inſtead of ſports and paſtimes, feel the torments of a damned Conſcience, then will he curſe his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humet,</hi> the day wherein he was born, and the womb that bare him. <hi>Quantum muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ab illo?</hi> How is the man now changed, when he ſeeth all his hopes fruſtrate, and for a World of happineſs falls into a deep confus'd <hi>Tophet,</hi> where the breath of the Lord, like a river of Brimſtone doth kindle it. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 30.33. <hi>No man cometh unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but by me,</hi> (ſaith the Way in my text) and if he gains heaven without Faith on Chriſt, farewell thou Queen of Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſacred Divinity, the Holy Scriptures then are but meer Riddles. But O God! thy word is truth, and all men beſides are liars; We know and believe. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Son hath everlasting life, and he that believeth not the Son, ſhal not ſee life
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34472:8"/>but the wrath of God abideth on him, John</hi> 3.36 And <hi>Veriſſimum eſt,</hi> this is moſt true, <hi>Whoſoever denyeth the Son, the ſame hath not the Father; but he that acknowledgeth the Son, hath the Father alſo.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.23. And again, <hi>He that honoreth not the Son honoureth not the Father that hath ſent him.</hi> John 5.23. Where are our Jews now, and Antitrinitarians, thoſe brethren in evill as (<hi>Jacob,</hi> ſaid of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi>) If the great <hi>Turk</hi> cannot be ſaved, what will be come of them? 3. <hi>Mutato nomine,</hi> change but only the name, and there is not a pair of ſheares between them. Poor Jew, (wert thou as rich as he of <hi>Malta</hi>) thou canſt never obtain true happineſs 'till thou believeſt in that God whom thy Fathers crucified. All thy priviledges and prerogatives which thou ſo much glorieſt in, without <hi>faith</hi> in him, will prove ſo many plummets of lead to ſink thy floating ſoul to Hell. Thou ſaiſt, thou haſt <hi>Abraham</hi> to thy Father, and thinkſt that ſhall carry it, a meer flouriſh. What armes canſt thou ſhew of his to prove thy pedegree. Hear what our Lord ſaid to thy <hi>Country</hi>-men of old; <hi>Your Father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34472:8"/>rejoyced to ſee my day, and he ſaw it, and was glad,</hi> John 8.56. The touring Eagle ownes no bird for hers that cannot out-look the Sun. Where is thy faith to make thy words good? The Philoſopher ſtared upon a Star, when he fell into a pit.</p>
            <p>In the next place I muſt ſay ſomething to our Roman Catholicks, who like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-men look one way and row another; theſe ſet too great a price on their works, and where natural beauty fails, there they ſeek to repair by Art. What with their Saints, and what with their works, Chriſt the only and true way is forgotten. We confeſs, the Mother of our Lord was a holy Virgin, a rich and pure Cabinet, wherein was incloſed that moſt precious Jewel (God-Man,) the true <hi>Catholicon,</hi> by whoſe blood all the diſeaſes and mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of our Souls occaſioned by ſin, were perfectly cured; and ſhe now a glorious Saint in Heaven; yet to make her a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is high Sacriledge. <hi>O my ſoul, come not thou into their ſecret, unto their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly mine honour be not thou united.</hi> Hear, and bluſh to hear it, <hi>Marie</hi> is the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34472:9"/>of our Salvation,<note place="margin">Maria eſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatrix noſtrae ſalvationis, &amp;c. Bernardinus in Mariali.</note> of our Conjunction, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Reconciliation, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, Communication. Mark what reſult that Den of Thieves, the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> give of the Saints in general, <hi>Sanctos ſupplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter invocare, &amp; ad eorum oratione opem, auxiliúmque confugere, bonum &amp; utile eſt.</hi> Humbly to invocate the Saints, and to fly to their prayers for help and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard is good and profitable. But again, ſee how they make their works ſit cheek by jowl with the merits of Chriſt. This is all one, to compare a ſtinking candle burnt to a ſnuff with the moſt tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent light, and glorious rayes of the Sun. Behold what a train they have in this particular, and with what rabble this Idol is uſhered up. Certainly theſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows muſt have a good purſe to maintain ſo great a retinue. Some by obſerving the preſcription and rule of (as they call them) S. <hi>Dominick, Frances, Benedick;</hi> and others the Saints, S. <hi>Bridget</hi> and S. <hi>Clare, &amp;c.</hi> others by their tedious pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinations to this or that Saint, others
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34472:9"/>by their Vigils, Maſſes, <hi>&amp; Roſariorum preculis,</hi> by their Roſary of ſhort prayers; others by their abſtinency, and faſting, <hi>&amp; ciborum delectibus,</hi> their choyce diſhes; others by a ſpontaneous whipping them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; others by their Alms-deeds (pity ſo good a pail of milk ſhould be ſpilt) <hi>aliiſque commentitiis pietatis operibus,</hi> and by other counterfeit works of godlineſs; they truly (though vainly) think to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Salvation, and more then ordinary reward in Heaven.</p>
            <p>But <hi>haec non eſt via, neque eſt haec civitas,</hi> this is not the way, neither is this the city, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Syrians,</hi> 2 Kings 6.19. This is not the way to Heaven, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will it ever bring any to that great city, <hi>the holy Jeruſalem deſcending out of Heaven from God,</hi> Revel. 21.10. I ſpeak not this to diſcourage a holy walking with God in a mans general or particular Calling, or that I null good works as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous and unneceſſary. No, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. <hi>Without holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord. Not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall be ſaved; but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven, Matth. 7.24.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34472:10"/>For as we are not ſaved <hi>propter opera,</hi> for our works, we are ſaved, and ſhall be one day judged accordingly, <hi>ſecundum opera,</hi> according to our works. <hi>See Matth.</hi> 25. v. 34. to the end. But I would not have men big with their works, high conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them, ſtand in competition with God, fondly to imagine their works me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious; in ſo doing they derogate from the free Grace of God, and the death and paſſion of Chriſt, who ſaith in my Text, <hi>I am the way, &amp;c. Alio nobis non opus eſt oſtiario, mediatore, vel miniſtro,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> We need no other door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, or Mediator, or Miniſter. 16. <hi>Hom. in Matth.</hi> Our Juſticiaries then and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Phariſees, like Players over act themſelves. Theſe indeed have good things in them, but (as we uſe to ſay) fools have them in keeping. Should we call them Papiſts they would ſpit at it, and yet verily in a ſence they are all one in this particular: juſt like the two El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in <hi>Suſanna</hi> they ſeem to take leave one of another, and preſently meet at one door. He that ſaith, <hi>I am the way</hi> ſaith likewiſe, <hi>I am the door of the Sheep.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34472:10"/>John</hi> 10.7. And as no man cometh unto the Father but by him ſo by him alſo <hi>we have acceſs by faith into the grace wherein we ſtand and rejoyce in hope of the glory of God.</hi> Rom 5.22. What impudence can out face that of the Apoſtle. <hi>For by grace are ye ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved through faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God, not of Workes, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt.</hi> Eph. 2.8, 9. And the ſame Apoſtle elſewhere ſaith, ſpeaking of free election; <hi>And if by grace then is it no more of works, otherwiſe grace is no more grace, but if it be of works; then it is no more grace, otherwiſe work is no more work.</hi> Rom. 11.6. Let the Church of Rome then tells what tale they pleaſe; I hope (beloved) it is no article in our Creed. To pray to Saints, and aſcribe merit to our works is the next way to make us devils. I am ſure they never had theſe puddles from the pure fountain of Gods holy word. Pride is one of the ſeven deadly ſins, but of two, ſpirituall pride is the more dangerous and muſt expect a fall. That man who is big with the timpany of his own worth will hardly acknowledg Chriſt to be the way. This is ſo ſtiff an
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34472:11"/>Oak that it will break rather then bend; and with <hi>Naball</hi> it is ſuch a ſon of <hi>Belial</hi> that a man cannot ſpeak to it. 1 Sam. 25.17. But to conclude the firſt particular, Let this ſerve for admonition to all that truely fear God, without procraſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to addreſs themſelves to Chriſt, who is, and none but he, the true and living way to bliſs: <hi>to know him and his Father is eternall life. John</hi> 17.3. Wherefore as the Apoſtle ſometime ſaid in another ſence, ſo let us all ſay; whether ſhall we go, thou haſt the words of Eternall life.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the ſecond branch in my Text. As Chriſt is the <hi>way,</hi> in like manner he is the <hi>truth.</hi> I am the <hi>truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt he is the <hi>truth Complendo,</hi> by way of accompliſhment, for in him as by a lively voice and promiſe, whatſoever was ſpoken and typified concerning the <hi>Meſſiah by the mouth of all the holy prophets, ſince the world began, are fulfilled.</hi> Acts. 3.21. ſee. v. 24. and. Acts. 10.43. In like manner, the whole Hierarchie of the Leviticall prieſthood is accompliſhed in him the Antetipe: which the Epiſtle to the Hebrews throughout plainly ſheweth.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34472:11"/>Thus the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Law, ſaith, that it was <hi>but a ſhadow of things to come,</hi> Hebr. 10.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly he is the <hi>truth Promittendo,</hi> by way of promiſe. So Joh. 17.17. <hi>Sanctifie them through thy truth, thy word is truth.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> thus ſpeaks Pſ. 119.43. <hi>And take not the word of truth utterly out of my mouth.</hi> And Pſ. 33.4. <hi>For the word of the Lord is right. Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but my words ſhall not paſs away. Luke.</hi> 21.33. St. <hi>Peter</hi> having ſpoken of the frailty and vanity of man and fleſh; poſitively concludes, <hi>that the word of the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly he is the <hi>truth Operando,</hi> by operation; becauſe by the holy Ghoſt through the word of <hi>truth, he ſhall guide us into all truth.</hi> Jo. 16.13. And Chapt. 8.31.32. <hi>If ye continue in my word then are ye my diſciples indeed, and ye ſhall know the truth, and the truth ſhall make you free;</hi> And v. 36. <hi>I the Son therefore ſhall make you free, ye ſhall be free indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may firſt ſerve to inform us, that Chriſt is the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that undoubted Seed of the woman who ſhould <hi>break, the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34472:12"/>Serpents head</hi> Gen. 3.8. That ſeed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> in whom all the nations of the earth were to be bleſſed. Gen. 12.3. <hi>He, who was to ſave his people from their Sins.</hi> Matth. 1.21. he in whom <hi>all the promiſes of God are yea and amen.</hi> 2. Cor. 1.20. Let us then who are Chriſtians acknowledge him alone to be our Saviour; although the Jews wickedly blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,<note place="margin">Parati ſunt adlegendam, cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci vero ad intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendum, duri ad credendum. Aug. Serm. 35. de Temp.</note> and fondly phancie themſelves of a <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come. Of whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truly ſpeaks; they are ready to read, but blind to underſtand, and hard to believe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if Chriſt is the <hi>truth,</hi> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, whatſoever is propounded to us, againſt, without, or beſides Chriſt to embrace and follow; is a meer lye. St. Paul calls it <hi>the Spirit of errour.</hi> 1. Tim. 4.1. Our Saviour himſelf ſaith <hi>There ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe prophets.</hi> Math. 24.24. That is to ſay: falſe Doctors and Teachers, as <hi>Tertuil.</hi> expounds the Text. <hi>Qui pſeudoprotae ſunt, niſi falſi praedicatores? Qui Pſeudo-apastoli, niſi adulteri Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizatores?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34472:12"/>Qui Antechriſti, niſi Chriſti re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles? de preſcript. haeret cap</hi> 4. Who are falſe prophets, but falſe preachers? Who are falſe Apoſtles, but adulterate Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers? Who are Antechriſts, but rebels of Chriſt? Theſe come in <hi>ſheeps cloathing,</hi> Matth. 7.15. <hi>Having a ſhew of Godlineſs.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. <hi>a ſhew of wiſdome.</hi> Coloſſ. 2.23. <hi>Who by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the Simple.</hi> Rom. 16.18. <hi>Yea they ſhall ſhow great ſigns and wonders, that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall deceive the very elect,</hi> Matth. 24.24. And indeed whom have they not deceived? If ever that ſaying was true, it is now; Where God hath his church there the devill hath his chappel. We have almoſt as many Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles as Churches, and a multitude reſort unto them. Let but one ſheep run aſtray and the whole flock will ſoon follow.<note place="margin">Et affabilisſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo &amp; blandum haereticorum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquium ſunt ſagena et laquens quibus piſces capiunt &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucres. In cap. 9. Eccl.</note> St. <hi>Hierom</hi> thus diſcribs the heretiques. Their affable ſpeeches, fair tongue are a gin and ſnare wherewith they catch the poor birds and fiſhes. But of theſe the people of God are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34472:13"/>admoniſhed to take heed, <hi>Beware of falſe prophets,</hi> ſaith our Saviour himſelf, Matth. 7.15. And in another place, <hi>Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Phariſees and of the Sadduces,</hi> chapt. 16.6. and that 24.25. and 26. verſ. read the words. And the diſciple follows his Maſter. Beloved, believe not every Spirit; but try the Spirits whether they are of God: and he giveth the reaſon; <hi>becauſe many falſe prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> 1 Epiſtle of John. 4. chapt. v. 1. Thus ſhould every Chriſtian do, if they would not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. Should a Goldſmith hand over head take all moneys without trying; I believe he would receive much adultera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted coine. To prevent which, he brings all to the touchſtone. If <hi>Solomon</hi> had not been wiſe, he could never known the true Mother, for the harlots were both a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hereſis Aocta eſt mentiri non tantum lingua, ſed &amp; vita; ſi fidem imerro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whil bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſttanius ſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſactonem nihil irreprehenſibilius. Bernd.</note> and in one tale. 1. Kin. 3.23. &amp;c. Wherefore, the beſt way to find out the falſe play of theſe juglers, is to bring them to the touchſtone of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34472:13"/>Gods word For all is not gold that gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. The property of Hereſie is to lye, not in tongue onely, but in Life. If thou queſtions his faith, not better Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; if his Converſation, none more ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reprehenſible; ſaith <hi>Benard.</hi> And <hi>Ireneus</hi> of falſe prophets, goes on thus; They ſpeak to us the ſame things,<note place="margin">Similia nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum loquuntur, diſſimilta vero ſentiunt lib. 1. epiſt. 59.</note> but think the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And truly had we not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the ſacred ſprings of holy Writ; the whole world would go after them. You know who ſaid it, <hi>My ſheep hear my voice,</hi> and again; The <hi>ſheep follow him, for they know his voice; And a ſtranger will they not follow but will flee from him. For they know not the voice of ſtrangers,</hi> John. 10.4.5. It was a voice from heaven which ſaid, <hi>hear him</hi> Matthew. 5.16. And he that came from Heaven, the Son of man who is in Heaven, ſaid of thoſe hypocrites, <hi>Mittite eos, Let them alone they be blind leaders of the blind, &amp;c.</hi> Matth. 15.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.</p>
            <p>In the next place; If Chriſt be the truth; then by conſequent, his word is truth; and we ought to ſubſcribe to it without diſpute. <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> was ſufficient
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34472:14"/>a Scholar of <hi>Pythagoras;</hi> If their Maſter once ſaid it, it carried as much weight with it, as delivered from an Oracle. Me thinks the word of God ſhould be of more credit with us. If that once ſpeakes, we ſhould preſently lay our hands upon our mounths, and by ſilence expreſs our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. <hi>I am with you unto the end of the world,</hi> that is, by his Spirit, Grace, word, &amp;c. <hi>Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> John 3.5. <hi>There are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one,</hi> 1 John 5.7. and verſe the 20. St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith, <hi>This is the true God and Eternal life.</hi> And according to St. <hi>Paul, God bleſſed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> Rom. 9.5. Theſe and whatſover we find recorded in the word, we muſt believe, without Cavelling; ſeem they never ſo contrary to naturall reaſon. This condemns the foul Hereſie of the <hi>Photinians,</hi> who deny the Divinity and Godhead of <hi>Christ;</hi> upon this account onely, becauſe their blind reaſons can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend it; as if our faith were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34472:14"/>pinn'd upon reaſons ſleeve. I have read of one who was in his dumps and deep contemplation, to define fully what God was; and this he would do forſooth by Phyloſophy and reaſon. In this his brown ſtudy, by the ſea-ſide, he ſeeth a Child go often to the ſea, and bringing from thence water in a ſhell, and then to put it in a little hole which was hard by. The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> asked the Child, why he did ſo; The Child replyed, becauſe I will bring all the Sea, and put it into this hole. That is impoſſible, ſaid the other again; So it is as impoſſible (ſaith the Child a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain) for thee by reaſon to define what God is. Worthy is that of <hi>Caſſianus;</hi> Doeſt thou ask me a reaſon of the Word. I do not tell thee; God hath ſaid it, his word is all the reaſon. The perſon of him alone that ſpeakes it is ſufficient for my belief. What need I enquire how that is true that God hath ſpoken, when I muſt not doubt, becauſe it is true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath ſpoken it. If this courſe were taken, it would not only prevent blaſphemy and miſtakes of Scripture, but be a great obſtruction to ſin and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34472:15"/>Did our <hi>Anapabtist</hi> but ſteer this way, they would not cavill ſo much at the Baptiſme of Infants. What though their baptiſme be not poſitive or demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative; yet it is deductive, deduced from Scripture, as plain as a mans noſe on his face. Will they play the thieves, and rob a poor Child of the Sacrament, upon this fond cavill, What good doth it doe them? And they have no faith, which is more then they can prove for they have Sacamentall faith, and the Seed of faith. And further they urge that Children are not capable of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo ought not to be baptized; As if that text had relation to the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Men and Women of ripe years; and not to Children. They make themſelves ſimple <hi>Logitians,</hi> for they underſtand not a diſtinction. If they ask what good it doth them;<note place="margin">Aqua corpus abſoluitur Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu animae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta mundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note>
               <hi>Saint Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> will tell them; The body is cleanſed by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, Water; the ſpots &amp; ſins of the Soul by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: I will end this with that of <hi>Cryſoſt.</hi> (meaning <hi>Tertullians</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34472:15"/>works) <hi>Da mihi Magiſtrum, da mihi Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrum, Give me my Maſter, give me my Maſter.</hi> So ſay I, and ſo let us all ſay of the word of God; <hi>da nobis Magiſtrum, &amp;c. Give us our Maſter, give us our Maſter.</hi> Thus Chriſt is the truth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as he is the <hi>way,</hi> and the <hi>truth</hi> ſo he is the <hi>life;</hi> and that in three reſpects, <hi>Creando &amp; Conſervando; Regenerando &amp; Sanctificando, Reſuſcitando &amp; Glorifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. By Creating and Conſerving us, By Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating and Sanctifying us, By Raiſing again and Glorifying us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt he is ſaid to be the <hi>Life,</hi> not ſo much in relation to his eſſence; in which reſpect he is <hi>life eternall,</hi> 1 <hi>John.</hi> 5.20. but in relation to us, in that he hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ared us, and kept us ever ſince by the hand of providence. So <hi>David, Pſalm.</hi> 100.3. <hi>Know ye that the Lord he is God, it is he that hath made us and not we our ſelves, we are his people, and the ſheep of his paſture.</hi> And the Apoſtle, <hi>In him we live, move, and have our being.</hi> Acts 17.28.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is <hi>life,</hi> and that eſpecially by Regenerating and by Conſerving us;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34472:16"/>becauſe, by the Sacraments and words, he workes, and (as I may ſo ſpeak) begets in us a <hi>Spirituall life.</hi> According to that of S. <hi>John, Jeſus anſwered, verily, verily I ſay unto thee, except a man be born of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of God,</hi> and ſo forward, John 35. And in the 6. chap. and 33. v. &amp;c. <hi>For the Bread of God is he which cometh down from Heaven, &amp;c.</hi> And John 10.10. I <hi>am come that they might have life, and that they might have it more abundantly.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath this expreſſion to the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, <hi>I am Crucified with Chriſt, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me; and the life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God; who loved me, and gave himſelf for me. Gal.</hi> 2.20. And in his Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans he ſaith, <hi>How ſhall we that are dead to ſin, live any longer therein? Know ye not that ſo many of us as were baptized into Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, were baptized into his death.</hi> Rom. 6.2. and v. 4. <hi>Therefore we are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him by baptiſme into death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed up from the dead by the Glory of the Father, even ſo we alſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34472:16"/>ſhould walk in newneſs of life.</hi> Read Rom. 8.12, 13.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and Laſtly, Chriſt is the <hi>life, Reſuſcitando &amp; Glorificando,</hi> by raiſing us again, and by glorifying us. <hi>This is the will of him that ſent me, that every one which ſeeth the Son, and believeth on him may have everlasting life; and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi> John 6.40. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I <hi>am the Reſurrection and the Life, he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live? And whoſoever liveth and believeth in me ſhall never dye.</hi> John. 11.25.26. St. Paul ſaith, <hi>whom he juſtifyed, them he alſo glorifyed.</hi> Rom. 8.30. And which is more; <hi>Who ſhall change our vile bodie, that it may be faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like unto his glorious body, &amp;c.</hi> Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians. 3.21.</p>
            <p>The fruit which we may gather from hence is this; If <hi>Chriſt</hi> be the <hi>life,</hi> we ſhould ſeek it in and through him only, without whom we ſhall never obtain it. And we ſhould not ſo much mind this preſent life, which we have in common with beaſts, reprobates; and as <hi>Eurip.</hi> ſaith <hi>Non vita, ſed calamitas eſt,</hi> It is not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34472:17"/>a life in compariſon, but a calamity, and differs nothing from death; if we believe the <hi>Phyloſopher:</hi> a life that is as brittle as Glaſs, frail and Momentany. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t hora ſic vita.</hi> It is a life, which paſſeth away as an hour upon the Diall, inſenſibly. But mind we that ſpirituall life of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and ſanctification, which is the life properly; and by which we live to <hi>God</hi> through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord. A life wherein ſin doth not reign in our mortall body, that we ſhould obey it in the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, neither yield we our members as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of unrighteouſneſs to ſin.</hi> Rom. 6.12, 13. When the Emperour <hi>Nero</hi> had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his houſe, which he called <hi>Domum Aureum,</hi> the golden houſe, he ſaid, now I begin to live like a man. <hi>But this is moſt true;</hi> we never begin to live like Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an men, till we live the life of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Sanctification. And now if Chriſt be our life. death will be to us advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. As St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath it. <hi>When Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, then ſhall ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appear with him in glory.</hi> Coloſſ. 3.4. And that true and eternall life which we here poſſeſs by faith and hope; We ſhall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34472:17"/>at length have the full fruition of it in <hi>Heaven.</hi> That of the Apoſtle is worthy of all acceptation; <hi>For whether we live, we live unto the Lord, and whether we dy, we dy unto the Lord; whether we live therefore of dy we are the Lords.</hi> Rom. 14.8. Who is he then that will not from his heart breath forth and ſay. O my Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thou art truly the way, becauſe no man cometh unto the Father <hi>niſi per te,</hi> but by thee; thou art the truth, becauſe no man knoweth the Father <hi>niſi per te,</hi> but by the Thou art the life, becauſe no man liveth, <hi>niſi per te,</hi> but by thee, Be thou to me the way by which I may come to thee and the Father; Be thou to me the truth by which I may know thee and the Father; be thou to me the life by which I may here live in thee by faith in believing, and there in heaven by fruition. Let this ever ſound freſh in our ears.<note place="margin">Ambularevis? ego ſum via; fallinonvis? ego ſum veritas: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rino<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vis? Ego ſum vita Hoc dicit ſalvator tuus, non eſt quo eas niſi ad me, non eſt quo cas niſi per me. Aug. Tract. 22 Johannum.</note> Wilt thou walk? I am the way, Wilt thou not be deceived: I am the truth; Wouldſt thou not dye? I am the life. This thy Saviour ſaith, thou haſt not where to go, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34472:18"/>unto me, nor how to go but by me. Secondly, if Chriſt be the life, then it follows there is a reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body at the laſt day. From this flower may the Bee ſuck honey, the Spider poyſon.</p>
            <p>Now in the firſt place, may the people of God, with the <hi>Eunuch</hi> depart home rejoycing, with much harmony in their Souls. <hi>Cura thymo pleno,</hi> their thighs are now laden with ſweetneſs. O the rare contentment of a child of God in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and want of all external comforts! With <hi>Jacob</hi> he may well &amp; truly ſay, few and evill have the dayes of my life been: As for this world he doth but breath in it, that is all. Yet prithy erect thy ſelf, baniſh thy ſad thoughts; no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is perpetuall; a ſtorm laſts not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes: The poor Ship that's long toſſed too and fro with a tempeſt gaines the wiſhed Port at laſt. The Ark that was hurried on the flood, hath a <hi>Dove</hi> with an <hi>Olive branch</hi> in her mouth to imitate the falling of the waters. <hi>Haec non dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt aetatem,</hi> as that learned Biſhop <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:34472:18"/>ſaid of the <hi>Marian</hi> perſecution. Theſe things will not laſt an age. Chear up ſweat heart; Gods rod is but a love kiſs, and our afflictions are but tokens of his indulgency. Look back to former Ages, and the Church is often in a cloud her throws like a woman in Travell, have been thick and painfull; <hi>Sicut un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſequitur undam,</hi> and have followed as one wave upon the neck of another. Yet mark the reſult of all; her end is peace at the laſt; Wait then with patience, and thou ſhalt ſee the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God; who ever truſted in him and was confounded? Behold a moſt ample compenſation: For thy light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, thou ſhalt have an exceeding, an eternall weight of glory in another World, Forget not the Text; <hi>I am the life, &amp;c.</hi> A day therefore will come when thy ſorrows will have an end, and breath out their laſt. Hear, and glut thine ear with this muſick. Ye are they which have continued with me in my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, and I appoint unto you a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as my Father hath appointed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; that ye my eat and drink at my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34472:19"/>table in my Kingdom, and ſit on thrones judging the twelve tribes of <hi>Iſrael. Luke</hi> 22.28. &amp;c. When this <hi>Sun</hi> once Sets and the great World on fire; they every man ſhall receive according to his works, and a full ſatisfaction made of all injuries and wrongs, which the poor <hi>Saints</hi> have groaned under in this Life by wicked and ungodly men.</p>
            <p>In the next place this may ſerve for horrour and amazement to all ſuch, who with <hi>Davids</hi> fool have ſaid in their hearts there is no God. The <hi>Sadduces</hi> and <hi>Epicures</hi> of our days who by their lives deny the reſurrection of the body. Some have likened a <hi>Courtier</hi> without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, to a <hi>Blackamoor, qui in ortu ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis poſitus, habet colorem noctis,</hi> who though living upon the <hi>Sun riſing,</hi> hath notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Colour of the night. So an <hi>Atheist</hi> amongſt us may fitly be compared to this <hi>Ethiopian;</hi> He liveth where the <hi>Sun riſeth,</hi> even where the Goſpell caſts forth its glorious beams; and yet he acts the works of darkneſs and of the night. It is obſerv'd by <hi>Joſephus,</hi> that the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces</hi> were moſt approved and favoured
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34472:19"/>by great men; And it is very probable; becauſe they that wallow in wealth, for the moſt part are ſo glued to this world, that they could wiſhed there were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and truly in their account there is not.<note place="margin">Nemo tam car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xaliter vivit, quam qui negat reſurrectionem.</note> That of <hi>Tertull.</hi> is undenyable No man liveth ſo looſely and Carnally, as he that denyeth the reſurrection of the body. And one may give a ſhrewd gueſs, that they who live in all kinds of pleaſures and voluptuouſneſs, <hi>&amp; luxuriant in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium operibus,</hi> and Pride it in ſilks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all fear of God, reverence to his houſe, love to his ordinances, and Charity to the poor: are <hi>Epecuri de grege porci;</hi> the hogs of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no life but the preſent. You ſhall allways have them Sing this Song. <hi>Ede, bibe, Lude, &amp;c. Eat, drink, and be merry, after death theres no pleaſure;</hi> I believe it; and will one day find by wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if they repent not before they go hence, and be no more ſeen. It were happy for worldly men if there were no reſurrection, they ſhould come then to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34472:20"/>no accompts. And on the contrary, the <hi>Saints</hi> were moſt unhappy; <hi>For if in this Life onely we have hope in Chriſt we are of all men moſt miſerble,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. But Chriſt is <hi>the Life, Reſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tando, &amp;c.</hi> by raiſing thee again, (as I ſaid before) God is juſt, and he will one day reward every man according to his works; and this muſt be in another world. Thou muſt not think to live heer a <hi>Devill,</hi> and a <hi>Saint</hi> hereafter; have the full fruition of happineſs in this world, be clad in purple and fine linnen, and fare deliciouſly <hi>quotidie,</hi> every day; &amp; at length be carried by <hi>Angels</hi> into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams boſome; Somnias vigilans,</hi> Thou dreameſt waking, once to think it. You know what was ſaid to the rich glutton being in hell torments, <hi>Mememto fili; Son remember that thou in thy life time receivedst thy good things, and likewiſe Lazarus his Evil things; but now he is comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi> Luke 16.25. Mark how Empatheticall the pronoune (Thy) is there. This life is called his life; not in regard he lived in it, for ſo it is every mans; but becauſe he ſo lived in it, as if
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34472:20"/>there had been no other Life beſides. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum non agnoſcit niſi preſens;</hi> A Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man acknowledgeth no World but the preſent; or at leaſt, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no other, till he drops into it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares. Hence it is, that he hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thought of death or of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Not unlike unto the Emperour <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> who ſeing at one time two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous preſages of his end, to wit <hi>a bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Comet</hi> and a gaping <hi>Sepulchre;</hi> puts them both from himſelf, and ſaid; the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> gaped for the <hi>Empreſs Julia,</hi> and the <hi>Star</hi> did portend only the death of the <hi>Perſian King,</hi> who then wore long hair. <hi>Cuſpind. Luſt.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou wilt not leave my Soul in grave, nor ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption,</hi> ſpeaking of of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Pſ. 16.10. <hi>My Soul in grave,</hi> there's the immortality of the Soul, <hi>nor ſuffer thy holy one to ſee Corpuption,</hi> there's the Reſurection of the body. That of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> who lay three dayes buried in the belly of a <hi>Whale,</hi> is <hi>Sacramentum mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> not only a true Hiſtory, but a preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant myſtery of the Reſurrection. <hi>Cor terrae fit venter ceti.</hi> The heart of the earth to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34472:21"/>us will be as the belly of the <hi>Whale</hi> was to <hi>Jonas;</hi> It ſhall not ever retain us. Death is the convoy or paſſing boat either to a better or ſadder port. In the time of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, God took away away <hi>Enoch,</hi> in the time of the law <hi>Elias,</hi> in the time of Grace our Saviour, himſelf: by all theſe examples, it is cleer; that we ſhall riſe again. The Scripture makes mention of four keyes, which God hath reſerved to himſelf. The firſt is <hi>Clavis pluviae,</hi> the key of rain. as <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.12. <hi>The Lord will open to thee his good treaſure.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is <hi>Clavis Cibationis,</hi> the key of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualls. Pſ. 145.16. <hi>Thou openeſt thy hand, and fillest every thing with thy plenteouſneſs.</hi> The third is <hi>Clavis Sterilitatis,</hi> the key of Sterility or barrenneſs. Gen. 30.22. Where it is ſaid <hi>God remembred Rachel, and opened her womb.</hi> The laſt is <hi>Clavis Sepulchrorum,</hi> the key of the grave. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.12. <hi>When I ſhall open your Sepulchres.</hi> But to omit Gods omnipotency, which is the <hi>baſis</hi> and fundametall arch, on which is founded our Chriſtian Religion; I will reduce all to two heads, his mercy, and his juſtice; Which two are the Maſter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34472:21"/>attributes which ſet all the reſt on work It is thus ſaid by God, <hi>I am the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac and the God of Jacob; Now God is not God of the Dead but of the Living. Matth.</hi> 22.32. He is not a God of thoſe that are not, who are without exiſtance, but of thoſe that have a being, ſo that he will raiſe their bodies at the laſt day. Otherwiſe, he ſhall <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midium tantunimodo hominum reſtituere;</hi> he were God to one part of <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But his mercy is over all his works.</hi> Pſ. 145.9 and extends both to Soul and Body; and <hi>in the mercy of the moſt high they ſhall not miſcarry.</hi> Pſ. 21.7. Secondly, as his Mercy, ſo his Juſtice requires a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Reſurection, when both the godly and the wicked ſhall come forth: their graves the one, <hi>rapi in occurſum,</hi> to meet the Lord in the Clouds, and the other <hi>verti retrorſum,</hi> to be turned down to Hell, with all thoſe that forget God. There muſt be a Judgment of Retribution in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World which cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Reſurrection of the body. The ungodly are ſometimes plagued in this life, to aſſure us there if a God; yet but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34472:22"/>ſometimes to aſſure us there is a day of judgment; wherein the accounts of all men and women muſt be audited and caſt up, <hi>In that day will God make up his jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells. Mal.</hi> 3.17. And put a difference between an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> and an <hi>Egyptian.</hi> Then will the Wheat be put into the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of Heaven, and the tares burnt in the fire. <hi>Surgite mortui,</hi> Ariſe ye dead, was St. <hi>Hieroms</hi> Earwig, and oftimes beat an alarum on his very heart ſtrings. Methinks that of the Apoſtle ſhould make us tremble; <hi>We ſhall ſtand before the judgment ſeat of Chriſt.</hi> O ſinner! Let the day of death and the day of doom be the two Pole-ſtars to fix alwayes thine eyes upon. I could wiſh (ſaith one) that men every where would diſcourſe of hell, <hi>nam ghehennam memineſſe, in ghehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam non permitter incidere.</hi> For the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of hell would by (Divine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) keep us from falling into it. I hope by this time (if thou beeſt not an Atheiſt) thou art convinced of this truth, that as Chriſt is the way and the truth ſo alſo he is the life; by whoſe omnipotent power we ſhall all one day riſe from our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34472:22"/>graves, to anſwer for what we have done in this life whether good or bad. I will now conclude. <hi>The day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night, in the which the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noyſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, the Earth alſo, and the workes that are therein ſhall be burnt up. Seeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolv'd, what manner of perſons ought ye to be in all holy Converſation and Godlineſs.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10, 11.</p>
            <p>Gloria Deo in excelſis. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
